<article
	 xmlns:r="http://www.r-project.org"
	 xmlns:c="http://www.C.org"
	 xmlns:omg="http://www.omegahat.org">

<info>
    <author>
     <personname>
       <firstname>Duncan</firstname>
          <surname>Temple Lang</surname>
        </personname>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>UC Davis</orgname>
         <orgdiv>Data Science Initiative</orgdiv>
        </affiliation>
   </author>
</info>

<title>Goals of Object Oriented Programming</title>

<para>
OOP involves being  more intentional about developing software, in contrast to interactive commands
and scripting. It is one step beyond writing functions, both literally and conceptually.
We are describing structures of related objects, how we act on them, how they are related.
</para>

<para>
The key goals of OOP are to make code more flexible, adaptible and reusable
but without having to change the code itself.

<ol>
<li> Allow extensions to change the way an existing function works without changing the code of that function, via
     generics and methods.</li>
     <li> Provide uniform interfaces to different functionality via generics and methods</li>
<li> Formal definitions of representation of objects of a class and constraints on the contents to ensure an object is valid</li>
</ol>  
</para>



<para>
  In S4, we tend to use direct inheritance.
  I write many coercion/as methods to convert from one class to another (across the classes not up and down the
  inheritance hierarchy).
</para>



<para>
  When we see
<r:function><![CDATA[
foo = function(x, ...)
{
    if(is(x, 'A'))
      ...
    else if(is(x, 'B'))
      ...
    else if(is(x, 'C'))
      ...    
}
]]></r:function>
then we should be thinking classes and methods.

<r:code>
setGeneric("foo", function(x, ...) standardGeneric("foo"))
</r:code>
<r:code>
setMethod("foo", "A", function(x, ...) { # code for A })
setMethod("foo", "B", function(x, ...) { # code for B })
setMethod("foo", "C", function(x, ...) { # code for C })
</r:code>
The code for these three cases are now  separate, easier to read and easier to reuse and adapt.
</para>
<para>
If we wanted to extend the original function   <r:func>foo</r:func> to support a class D,
we'd have to add an <r:expr eval="false">else if(is(x, "D"))</r:expr> clause.
If we do this, we have to retest all of our code as this could break something.
If we don't own the function <r:func>foo</r:func>, we'd have to either 1) make a copy
of it and now maintain it ourselves and integrate changes from the original foo as it
evolves, or 2) petition the owner to add code for class D.  In 2),
foo's original package may not even have a definition for D, so adding code for it would be
inappropriate, or at least strange.
</para>

<para>
  Using methods, however, removes the need for 1) and 2) above.
  We clearly don't have to change the original <r:func>foo</r:func> if it is a generic function, so that solves 1).
  Addressing 2), any user can define a method for <r:func>foo</r:func> in any package.
  The original author of <r:func>foo</r:func> or the classes A, B, and D do not have to be involved.
</para>





</article>
